A Guide to the Melville Elijah Stone Papers 1821-1984
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Melville Elijah Stone Papers 1821-1984
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11091
There are 350 items in this collection (1 Hollinger box and 1 oversize box).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This material was purchased by the Library on April 14, 1993, from James Cummins Bookseller, New York City.
Scope and Content Information
This collection of materials pertaining to the sport of cock-fighting, ca. 1821-1984. The nucleus of this collection consists of the illustrative materials assembled by Melville Elijah Stone (1848-1929), American publisher and author, for his proposed book Cock-Fighting and The Game-Cock, Being an Illustrated Compendium of their History in Sport & Art From most Ancient Times to the Present Day To which is added A Bibliography, and the author's original layout for this unpublished book.
This layout, circa 1929, with the author's bookplate laid in, consists of 16 eight-page signatures (pages measuring 10 x 13) with pencilled layout instructions in the author's hand, along with the dedication page incorporating some small sketches, and other handwritten front matter from which we learn that the book was to be designed by William A. Kittredge, printed by Chicago's Lakeside Press on handmade Japanese paper, published by the Huntington Press, New York, in 1932, and limited to 200 copies. The book's title, half-title, and publisher imprint have been set in type and pasted in, and at the end are twelve pages of rough pencil sketches by the author illustrating glassware, cups, etc., with cock-fighting motifs. Also placed in the layout volume are about sixty examples of wild fowl, possibly to be used as illustrations for the first chapter, "The Origin of the Game Fowl."
The illustrations assembled by Stone for his book include engravings, prints, original artwork, sketches, magazine and book illustrations, an original title page for Henry Alken's (1784-1851) British Sports, and illustrations of cock-fighting objects d'art. There are a few illustrations from ancient times but most are concerned with the modern era, with particular emphasis on 18th Century England. Most of these are oversize and are housed in oversize folders. A detailed listing is provided at the end of the guide.
Also included are six small leatherette loose-leaf notebooks (undated) kept by Melville Stone with notes and other material pertaining to his cock-fighting history. These contain the names and addresses of scholars and other contacts about the history of cock-fighting and other related topics, filed alphabetically according to the name of the country or geographic area; clippings and photostats which include Stone's typewritten table of contents for the proposed volume and numerous notes for the text and captions; a bibliography of works dealing with cock-fighting, arranged alphabetically in two notebooks; notes for an index to the book; and an alphabetical index of various artists and their work on cock-fighting.
There is additional printed, photostatic and photographic material about cock-fighting, some of which post dates the death of Stone and must have been included by someone else. This material includes newsclippings and articles (1926-1984), a few pages of loose notes, photographs, both positive and negative photostatic copies of excerpts from The Sportsman's Magazine, issues 1823- 1825, about cock-fighting, and a twelve page typescript "Feathered Warriors" by Morris Markey.
The folder of photographs contain black & white photographs of engravings and paintings of game cocks, "A Copy of an article for a Cock-Match" in 1751, a chair used by a spectator at a cock fight, snapshots illustrating the proper handling of cocks, a stone relief of cock-fighting from the Art Institute of Chicago, plates and cups with cock-fighting scenes, and title pages of works on cock-fighting.
Contents List
- MELVILLE ELIJAH STONE PAPERS
  - Layout for Cock-Fighting and The Game-Cock, Being an Illustrated Compendium of their History in Sport & Art, compiled by Melville E. Stone, II, including sixty examples of wild fowl presumably to be used as illustration for Chapter One, "The Origin of the Game Fowl," and blocks sketched out to feature the paintings of Henry Alken, James Barringer, Edwin Cooper, Ben Marshall, J.N. Sartorius, H. Turner, a prints section, and a "bric-a-brac" section ca. 1929 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Material re: Cock-Fighting, including the title page for The Sporting Magazine(1853), and a pen-and-ink drawing of a cock fight (with photographs of the drawing) 1853-1952, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Newsclippings & Articles re: Cock-Fighting 1926-1984, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Notebooks containing alphabetically arranged notes concerning cock-fighting including the names and addresses of contact persons by area of expertise; artists and their work; notes for a bibliography (2 volumes) and an index; and clippings, photostats, and typed table of contents for the book n.d., 6 notebooks (Box 1)
  - Photographs re: Cock-Fighting n.d. (Box 1)
  - The Sportsman's Magazine-- Excerpts from 1823-1825 issues re: Cock-Fighting (Positive & negative photostatic Copies) n.d. (Box 1)
  - Typescript "Feathered Warriors" by Morris Markey n.d., 12 pages (Box 1)
  - "Isla De Cuba Valla De Gallos" n.d., color engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Un Indio Banquero," 1817, watercolor, with a pencilled hand-written note, "fort in harbor of Manila, Philippino Gambling Banker Cock-Fighting, Paper Watermarked 1817" (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "A Battle Between A Birchen Pile and a Black-breasted Tawny Duck-Wing" n.d., color engraving, London, Printed for R. Sayer & J. Bennett (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Cock-fighting" New Orleans 1852, black & white engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Der Hahnen Kampf Cocks Fighting" Museum in Berlin [After Frans Snyders] n.d., 2 black & white engravings and a photograph (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "A Combat of Cocks" n.d., black & white engravings from the original painting in The Museum of the Luxembourg by Jean Louis Gerome (1824-1904); 3 copies. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Les Deux Rivaux" -- L. Cherelle, black & white engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Venizia, R. Acc. -- Hondecoeter: Combattimento di galli" n.d., postcard (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Le Coq Reveil-Matin vous donne l'intelligence De l'embleme de la vigilance (No. 150)" n.d., color print made from a woodblock (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Untitled ["Sold by F. Bull en Ludgate Hill, London?], black & white engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Two colorful cocks created by gluing down feathers on boards, with beaks and feet drawn in n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Cock-Fight" by Carton Moorepark n.d., black & white print, with a letter from Carton Moorepark to Melville Stone, 1931 Jun 23 (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Black & white engraving of two medallions on one page, the first with two cocks fighting over a stalk of grain in one's mouth, and the other with two cocks fighting over a stalk of grain being stolen by a mouse above their heads n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Sportsman's Levee" engraved for the Carlton House Magazine n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Old Cock Pits at Lymme Hall, Cheshire, England, The Ancestral Home of the Domville Family" by H. Atty 1931 April 16, pen-and-ink drawing (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Cock Pit An Original Sketch From Which It is Presumed Hogarth Took His Well-Known Picture" by A. Ducotes Lithographer, published by T. McLean 1837 Feb 16, black & white engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Meta Puazo!" by Argentina's well-known artist Al Pargatas n.d., color print (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Cock Pit From the Original by Hogarth" engraved by G. Presbury n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Pit Ticket" (similar to Hogarth's) n.d., black & white engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Cock-Match" n.d., black & white engraving with text discussing "Pit Ticket" and Hogarth's work re: cock-fighting (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Cock Fighting" by [Henry Alken?] and "Pit Ticket" by Hogarth n.d., 2 prints on single page; Alken one in color & Hogarth one in black & white (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Thus we poor COCKS exert our skill and brav'ry, For idle GULLS and kites, that trade in KNAV'RY (1785)" 1785, black & white engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Cock Pit" by Presbury n.d., black & white engraving by Presbury from the original by Hogarth with several entries from a journal or magazine also glued to the page (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed list of books sold by J. Barker, including Directions for Breeding Game Cocks, with a small copy of a print about cock-fighting, and "The Earliest Picture of Cock-fighting" from a fresco at Pompeii taken from an illustration in a magazine n.d., on a single page (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Combat de Cocs en Flandre" (Salonde 1889) by Remy Cogche 1889 (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Untitled -- two cocks prepare for battle n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled -- two cocks standing apart n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled -- two cocks fighting with one down on the ground n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copies of "The Set-to" and "The Victory" by Edwin Cooper (1816) published by R. Ackermann n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copies of "Spooner's Transformations No. 7 The Rival Heroes or a Fight For the Championship 1836 Jun 18" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copies of The Sporting Magazine Plates "Ginger Red" and "Birchin Yello" (1792 Dec) and "Cock Pit Royal (1796)" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copy of The Sporting Magazine plate of cock-fighting on the cover, 1797 Apr n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copies of The Sporting Magazine Plates "Pit Ticket" (1797 Apr) & "Cocks Sparring" (1805 Dec) n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copies of The Sporting Magazine Plates "Game Cock" (1810 Jul) and "Game Cock & Fox" after D. Higgins (1821 Jun) n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copy of The Sporting Magazine Plate "Game Cocks" by Lambert Marshall (1831 Dec 1) n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Sporting Magazine Plate "Joseph Gilliver" engraved by P. Roberts after W. Webb (1834) n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of a scene "Sketched in the Cockpit at Nottingham Aug 1801, drawn on the spot" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of a sketch of a cock fight [used as basis for "The Royal Pit"] n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographic Copy of the black & white engraving "Royal Cock Pit," London, published May 1808 at R. Ackermann's Repository of Arts n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Photograph Copy -- two cocks about to "set-to" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Photographic Copy -- one cock victorious with another dead in the field n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Photographic Copy -- three fowls eating grain n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Three photographs of entries from the diary of Samuel Pepys' with transcriptions of the shorthand manuscript, on three pages, concerning cock-fighting n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Three photographs of "The Last Dying Speech and Confession of John Billingsgate" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled engraving of an apparently wooden cock pit with a three row semicircular seating arrangement for the spectators, showing two cocks in a bout n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of the title pages for Henry Alken's British Sports(1820), The National Sports of Great Britain(1821 and 1825), Sporting Scrap Book(n.d.), the book cover for Alken's Sporting Scrap Book(n.d.), a page taken from Henry Alken's Scrap Book, and the text for "Cock-Fighting" taken from The National Sports of Great Britain(1825), all published in London by Thomas M'Lean n.d., 8 photographs (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of the title pages for Henry Alken's Sporting Sketches; consisting of Subjects Relating to the Sports of the Field...The Whole Illustrative of Landscape Scenery(1817, 1821, n.d.) all published in London by S. and J. Fuller n.d., 3 photographs (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of two illustrations from Henry Alken's Sporting Sketches(1817, 1821) n.d., 2 photographs (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of the title page The Cocker: A Poem in Imitation of Virgil's Third Georgic Humbly Inscribed to the Honourable Society of Sportsmen at Grantham by Isaac Hallam, Stamford: Printed by Francis Howgrave, 1742 n.d., 3 photographs (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of the plate and article on "The Gamecock" in The Sportsman's Magazine for the week ending September 13, 1845 n.d., 3 photographs (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs by W.J. Roege, New York, of two commemorative silver cups with cock-fighting scenes and the inscriptions "Wednesbury Grey beating Red Robin W.E.R." and "Wednesbury Grey beating E. Peel's Hector 1803" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The original title page for Henry Alken's British Sports, 1821 1821, color engraving (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Cock Fighting Plates 1 & 2" by Henry Alken, January 1, 1820 n.d., 2 color engravings by I. Clark (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Copy of "The Champion. Bred by the late J. Clarke of London, the winner of many Matches, published by R. Pollard & Sons, April 16, 1823" n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Copy of "Yorkshire Hero. The Winner of Twenty Seven Battles !!!" published by R. Pllard & Sons, April 16, 1823 n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copy of "Phenomenon. Bred by Thomas Clark of Vauxhall, The Winner of the Gold Cup at Westminster & of Seven Long Mains" published by R. Pollard & Sons, March 15, 1824 n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Copy of "The Cheshire Pile. Bred by the Rt. Honorable the Earl of Derby" published by R. Pollard & Company, May 18, 1826 n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of "Cock Fightin" Plates 1-4, after Henry Alken, engraved by Sutherland, no background, and originally published January 1, 1818, by S. Knight n.d., 2 pages, black & white (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of "Cock Fighting" Plates 1-4, after Henry Alken, engraved by Sutherland & Harris, with background, published Spetember 1, 1841, by R. Ackermann n.d., 2 pages, black & white (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Two color prints by Henry Alken, "Cock Fighting," pattern for the engravings of above Plates 1 & 4 n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of 6 prints by Newton Fielding entitled "Set Too," "Fight," "Throat," "Knockdown," "Recovery," and "Death" from the Collection of F. Ambrose Clark n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Four Color Prints drawn by Henry Alken entitled "Set Too," "Right," "Throat," and "Death" and engraved by C.R. Stock n.d., 2 pages (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Untitled Color Print by [Henry Alken?] of a Cock Fight n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Two Color Prints by Henry Alken, Sr., entitled "York Won at Yarmouth Races 1840 again at Norwich same year" and "The Bishop Fought at Lincoln, February 4, 1834" from the Collection of F. Ambrose Clark n.d., 1 page (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Three black & white Currier & Ives Cock-fighting Scenes entitled "De Boss Rooster" (1882), "Copped At A Cock Fight Parson - Leff me go Boss, I only jis done go dar to reckinsile dem roosters" (1884), "A Main of Cocks, - The First Battle." (n.d.) 1882, 1884, n.d. (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Two photographs of black & white engravings if "The Game Cock. El Gallo De Pelea Trimmed and In Full Feather," n.d., 1 page (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Two black & white photographs of birds by Harry Lyman, 1886, entitled "M. Kearney's Ginger Red" and "M. Kearney's Brown Red" 1886, 2 pages (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 3)
  - This folder contains miscellaneous and illustrative material including an uncut sixteen page gathering of illustrations for Stone's book; three torn photographs of a Chinese cock-fighting scene from the Field Museum of Natural History; two photographs of cock-fighting scenes [paintings ?]; a printed cartoon of cocks fighting in front of uniformed officers with the caption, "Les officiers de la marine cuirassee envoyes aux combats de coqs pour y apprendre a se servir de l'eperor" on page 84 of Actualites, Paris, France; newsclippings about cock-fighting mounted on board, 1832-1899; "The Eton Cock Pit Discoveries" by Mary Stevens in The Illustrated London News, February 18, 1933; "The Fighting Cock and Other Fowl" by A. Rex Woods in The Field, January 7, 1965; and "The Brave and the Bold Game Cock" in The Field, April 11, 1968 ca. 1832-1968 (Box-folder OS Box 1, Folder 4)